

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER AT ETH ZÜRICH Hohlstrasse 510, 8048 Zurich, Switzerland

☐ (+41) 76 736 00 94 | ☐ leon@sering.eu | ☐ leon.sering | ☐ leon-sering | ☐ leon-sering |

Summary_

As a mathematician and computer scientist, I currently work as a Postdoc for the Institute for Operations Research at ETH Zürich. Beside my theoretical research on Nash flows over time (agent-based traffic modeling), my true passion lies in optimization algorithms and high performance algorithm design. I lead two exciting industry collaborations: For Swiss Post we solve a vehicle routing problem and for SBB I'm developing a high performance algorithm for optimal rolling stock scheduling. For more details visit my homepage: https://leon.sering.eu.

My programming language of choice? Rust. This high performance system programming language, with focus on parallelism/concurrency, is the perfect tool for my projects. Plus, it's just plain fun to use!

In my downtime, you will find me (and my family) exploring the wonders of our planet – through road trips, photography, and Scuba diving.

Work Experience _____

Operations Research Expert (Freelancer)

Paderborn, Germany

OPTANO GMBH

May 2023 - June 2023

- Consulting services for a line haul solution.
- Design of mixed-integer linear program.
- Implementation of a fast multi-objective routing algorithm.

Postdoctoral Researcher Zurich, Switzerland

INSTITUTE FOR OPERATIONS RESEARCH, DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS, ETH ZÜRICH

April 2021 - today

- Leading scientific collaboration with Swiss Post and Swiss Federal Railways SBB.
- Design and implementation of fast clustering algorithm.
- Research in operations research, efficient algorithms, meta-heuristics, and parallelism.

Research Associate Berlin, Germany

RESEARCH GROUP: COMBINATORIAL OPTIMIZATION & GRAPH ALGORITHMS, INSTITUTE OF MATHEMATICS, TU BERLIN

May 2017 - March 2021

- ECMath and MATH+ research projects: dynamic models and algorithms for equilibria in traffic networks.
- · Research goals: improve agent-based mathematical flow over time models (Nash flow over time) to connect with large-scale traffic simulations such as MATSim.

Education

Dr. rer. Nat. in Mathematics TU Berlin, Germany

DISSERTATION TITLE: NASH FLOWS OVER TIME, GRADE: SUMMA CUM LAUDE, MATH+ DISSERTATION AWARD

Sep. 2016 - Sep. 2020

• PhD topic: traffic simulation and optimization by using flows over time including game theoretical aspects.

Master of Advanced Studies University of Cambridge, UK

PART III OF THE MATHEMATICAL TRIPOS, GRADE: WITH HONOURS

Oct. 2013 - Jul. 2014

Bachelor and Master of Science in Mathematics

University of Würzburg, Germany

GRADES: 1.0 / 1.0, AWARDS: 2X OTTO-VOLK-MEDAL FOR EXCELLENT PERFORMANCES

Oct. 2010 - Sep. 2014

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

GRADE: 1.0, AWARD FOR EXCELLENT PERFORMANCES

University of Würzburg, Germany

Oct. 2010 - Apr. 2013

Selected Projects

_ leon.sering.eu/#projects

Rolling Stock Scheduling Optimization

ETH - SBB - Collaboration

LANGUAGES AND TOOLS: RUST | DOCKER | HTTP SERVER

- Scheduling trains (rolling stock) for a given time tabel to minimize dead head trips.
- Approach: local-search heuristic using concurrency and min-cost flow optimization.

LEON SERING · CV FEBRUARY 14, 2024

Fast Same-Day Delivery Optimization

LANGUAGES AND TOOLS: SCALA | GUROBI | DOCKER | HTTP SERVER

- Vehicle Routing: Scheduling capacitated drivers to deliver shipments within time windows.
- Approaches: mixed integer program, local search heuristic, fast k-opt for TSP-subproblem.

Fair and Fast k-Center Research Project at ETH Zürich

LANGUAGES: RUST | PYTHON

- Linear-time algorithm for k-center with fairness criteria that runs very fast in practice.
- Highly optimized for parallelism/concurrency.
- · ICML publication.

Nash Flow Computation

Research Project at TU Berlin

ETH - Swiss Post - Collaboration

LANGUAGES AND TOOLS: PYTHON | QT | SCIP

• Tool for computing Nash flows over time with mixed integer programming.

Drawing Road Networks with Focus Regions

Research Project

LANGUAGES AND TOOLS: JAVA | QT | CPLEX

- Tool for computing road network visualization with enlarged user-defined focus regions.
- TVCG publication.

Computer Skills _____

Computer Science

COMBINATORIAL OPTIMIZATION | META-HEURISTICS | FAST PARALLEL ALGORITHMS | MATHEMATICAL PROGRAMMING

Programming Languages

RUST | SCALA | PYTHON | JAVA

Optimization Tools

GUROBI | SCIP

Miscellaneous

GIT | GITLAB | GITHUB | BASH | NEOVIM | DOCKER | CI/CD | LATEX | LINUX | WINDOWS | OFFICE SOFTWARE

Scholarships and Competitions _____

Deutschlandstipendium

NATIONAL SCHOLARSHIP

University of Würzburg

May 2011 - Sep. 2015

Vereinigte Stipendien- und Preisstiftung

University of Würzburg

SCHOLARSHIP OF THE UNIVERSITY OF WÜRZBURG

Aug. 2010 - Apr. 2011

Award Winner in the Final Round of 26. Bundeswettbewerb Informatik

NATIONAL COMPETITION IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Dec. 2007 - Sep. 2008

High School

Languages

Fluent

English

Native

German

Interests

traveling | photography | scuba diving | running | computer games | virtual reality

FEBRUARY 14, 2024 LEON SERING · CV

Research Publications _____

leon.sering.eu/#publications

- [1] Christoph Hertrich and Leon Sering. "ReLU Neural Networks of Polynomial Size for Exact Maximum Flow Computation". In: *International Conference on Integer Programming and Combinatorial Optimization (IPCO '23)*. 2023. arXiv: 2102.06635.
- [2] Neil Olver, Leon Sering, and Laura Vargas Koch. "Convergence of Approximate and Packet Routing Equilibria to Nash Flows Over Time". In: *Annual Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS'23)*. IEEE. 2023. arXiv: 2402.04935.
- [3] Theresa Ziemke, Leon Sering, and Kai Nagel. "Spillback changes the long-term behavior of dynamic equilibria in fluid queuing networks". In: *Workshop on Algorithmic Approaches for Transportation Modelling, Optimization, and Systems (ATMOS'23)*. OpenAccess Series in Informatics (OASIcs). Dagstuhl, Germany, 2023.
- [4] Antonia Adamik and Leon Sering. "Atomic Splittable Flow Over Time Games". In: *Symposium on Algorithmic Foundations of Dynamic Networks (SAND'22)*. 2022, p. 53. arXiv: 2010.02148.
- [5] Haris Angelidakis, Adam Kurpisz, Leon Sering, and Rico Zenklusen. "Fair and Fast k-Center Clustering for Data Summarization". In: *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML'22)*. PMLR. 2022, pp. 669–702.
- [6] Neil Olver, Leon Sering, and Laura Vargas Koch. "Continuity, Uniqueness and Long-Term Behavior of Nash Flows Over Time". In: *Annual Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS'21)*. IEEE. 2022, pp. 851–860. arXiv: 2111.06877.
- [7] Leon Sering, Laura Vargas Koch, and Theresa Ziemke. "Convergence of a Packet Routing Model to Flows over Time". In: *Mathematics of Operations Research (MOR)* 0.0 (2022). A preliminary version was presented at the 22nd ACM Conference on Economics and Computation (EC'21). arXiv: 2105.13202.
- [8] Stefan Felsner, Linda Kleist, Torsten Mütze, and Leon Sering. "Rainbow Cycles in Flip Graphs". In: *SIAM Journal on Discrete Mathematics* 34.1 (2020). A preliminary version was presented at the International Symposium on Computational Geometry (SoCG'18), pp. 1–39. arXiv: 1712.07421.
- [9] Lukas Graf, Tobias Harks, and Leon Sering. "Dynamic Flows with Adaptive Route Choice". In: *Mathematical Programming* 183.1 (2020), pp. 309–335. arXiv: 1811.07381.
- [10] Jonas Israel and Leon Sering. "The Impact of Spillback on the Price of Anarchy for Flows over Time". In: *International Symposium on Algorithmic Game Theory (SAGT'20)*. Springer. 2020, pp. 114–129. arXiv: 2007.04218.
- [11] Hoang Minh Pham and Leon Sering. "Dynamic Equilibria in Time-Varying Networks". In: *International Symposium on Algorithmic Game Theory (SAGT'20)*. Springer. 2020, pp. 130–145. arXiv: 2007.01525.
- [12] Leon Sering. "Nash Flows Over Time". PhD thesis. Technische Universität Berlin, 2020.
- [13] Theresa Ziemke, Leon Sering, Laura Vargas Koch, Max Zimmer, Kai Nagel, and Martin Skutella. "Flows Over Time as Continuous Limits of Packet-Based Network Simulations". In: *Transportation Research Procedia* (2020). A preliminary version was presented at The Euro Working Group on Transportation (EWGT'20).
- [14] Leon Sering and Laura Vargas Koch. "Nash Flows Over Time with Spillback". In: *ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA'19)*. 2019, pp. 935–945. arXiv: 1807.05862.
- [15] Leon Sering and Martin Skutella. "Multi-Source Multi-Sink Nash Flows over Time". In: *Workshop on Algorithmic Approaches for Transportation Modelling, Optimization, and Systems (ATMOS'18)*. Vol. 65. OpenAccess Series in Informatics (OASIcs). Dagstuhl, Germany, 2018, 12:1–12:20. arXiv: 1807.01098.
- [16] Leon Sering. "A Combinatorial Upper Bound on the Length of Twang Cascades". In: European Workshop on Computational Geometry (EuroCG'17). Malmö, 2017, pp. 177–180.
- [17] Jan-Henrik Haunert and Leon Sering. "Drawing Road Networks with Focus Regions". In: *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics* 17.12 (2011). A preliminary version was presented at IEEE Information Visualization Conference (INFOVIS'11), pp. 2555–2562.